In the last video, we started to contract muscles. As you can see, we ran a simulation here with muscle activation.
지난 영상에서는 근육을 수축시키기 시작했죠. 보시다시피 여기서는 근육 활성화를 넣고 시뮬레이션을 돌렸습니다.
Now let's run some quick tests on just these muscles. So we can do that through a node called delete slash vertices.
이제 이 근육들만 대상으로 간단한 테스트를 해보겠습니다. 이를 위해 'Delete/Vertices'라는 노드를 사용하면 됩니다.
This will allow us to delete unnecessary vertices and run faster simulation tests.
이렇게 하면 불필요한 버텍스를 삭제해서 시뮬레이션 테스트를 더 빠르게 돌릴 수 있습니다.
So let's go ahead and at this point create a perfect selection that we want to delete.
그럼 이제 삭제하고자 하는 부분을 정확하게 선택해 보죠.
We can do that through painting. Let's go ahead and add a paint weight map node.
페인팅으로 할 수 있습니다. 'Paint Weight Map' 노드를 추가하겠습니다.
And I can paint on the muscles I want to keep. In this case, let's go ahead and flip fill.
그리고 유지하고 싶은 근육에 페인트합니다. 여기서는 플립 필(Flip Fill)로 전체를 채워보겠습니다.
Let's also keep the muscle that's providing constraints.
제약을 제공하는 근육도 유지하겠습니다.
Okay, that's a good amount. And let's give this a name for the attribute called the simulation test.
좋습니다, 이 정도면 충분하네요. 그리고 이 속성 이름을 'simulation_test'로 지정하겠습니다.
And we can extract the vertex selection here through the node called collection select by attribute.
'Collection Select by Attribute' 노드를 통해 여기서 버텍스 선택을 추출할 수 있습니다.
Let's connect attribute key. And over here for operation, because we're selecting vertices based on the attribute, the operation would be a threshold.
'Attribute Key'를 연결하고, 'Operation'은 속성 값을 기준으로 버텍스를 선택할 것이므로 'Threshold(임계값)'로 설정합니다.
So let's make sure we select everything above 0.5. So that means whatever we selected before should have attribute 1. Therefore they're selected.
그래서 0.5 이상인 것들을 모두 선택하도록 합니다. 즉, 아까 우리가 칠해 둔 부분은 속성 값이 1이므로 선택됩니다.
selected.
선택되었습니다.
Then we can connect the vertex selection here.
그다음 이 버텍스 선택 출력을 여기로 연결해 줍니다.
Remember, we're trying to delete the ones that are not selected.
기억하세요, 우리는 선택되지 않은 것들을 삭제하려는 겁니다.
So make sure we add invert operation.
따라서 'Invert(반전)' 옵션을 켜 주세요.
If we do that, we can connect vertex selection here.
그렇게 하면 이쪽에 버텍스 선택을 연결할 수 있습니다.
Now you can see we only keep these selected muscles.
이제 선택된 근육들만 남겨둔 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So this allows us to run some quick simulation tests.
이렇게 하면 빠르게 시뮬레이션 테스트를 할 수 있습니다.
Let's go ahead and connect the terminal.
'Terminal'을 연결하겠습니다.
Now you can see only these muscles are here.
이제 이 근육들만 존재하는 걸 확인할 수 있습니다.
We run a simulation now.
이제 시뮬레이션을 실행합니다.
You can see now it's much faster.
보시다시피 훨씬 빨라졌죠.
I think it was 1.6 seconds per frame.
프레임당 약 1.6초였던 것으로 기억합니다.
So we save about 75% of the time.
그러니 시간은 약 75% 절약됐네요.
Here, let's just let it finish.
여기서는 끝까지 마치도록 둡시다.
Here you can see the effect of the muscle contraction.
여기서 근육 수축의 효과를 볼 수 있습니다.
So let's go ahead and play with the muscle contraction parameter.
이제 근육 수축 관련 파라미터들을 조금 조정해 보죠.
We can do that in this node set muscle activation parameter.
이 노드, 'Set Muscle Activation Parameter'에서 조정할 수 있습니다.
Here, right now, we're using the default global parameters.
현재는 기본 글로벌 파라미터를 사용하고 있습니다.
So we can change the global parameters here.
여기서 글로벌 파라미터를 변경할 수 있습니다.
Volume contraction, volume scale.
볼륨 수축, 볼륨 스케일입니다.
This controls if muscle gains volume when it's contracting.
이 값은 근육이 수축할 때 볼륨이 얼마나 증가하는지 제어합니다.
So set that to 3.
이를 3으로 설정하겠습니다.
And if we run the simulation again, you should see the effect of that.
다시 시뮬레이션을 돌리면 그 효과가 보일 겁니다.
For the sake of the tutorial, let's go ahead and only keep the bicep.
튜토리얼 진행을 위해 이젠 이두근만 남겨 보겠습니다.
Right, now you should only see the bicep here.
좋아요, 이제 여기에는 이두근만 보일 겁니다.
Let's go ahead and start running the simulation.
그럼 시뮬레이션을 실행하죠.
Now you can see it's running it.
지금 실행 중인 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But when the bicep is contracting, you can see it gains a lot of volume
하지만 이두근이 수축할 때 볼륨이 상당히 늘어나는 것을 볼 수 있고,
because of that parameter here.
이는 여기의 해당 파라미터 때문입니다.
So there we have a quick test, quick way of testing muscle parameters.
이렇게 간단히 근육 파라미터를 테스트하는 방법을 살펴봤습니다.
Let's revert that.
이 설정은 원래대로 되돌리죠.
And things we can also change is that muscle fiber length ratio.
또 바꿀 수 있는 것이 '근섬유 길이 비율(Muscle Fiber Length Ratio)'입니다.
So if we decrease this, the muscle will contract harder towards the center.
이 값을 줄이면 근육이 중앙 쪽으로 더 강하게 수축합니다.
And we also have the muscle length ratio threshold.
'Muscle Length Ratio Threshold'도 있습니다.
So which means if your muscle...
즉, 근육이…
So at 0.75 means if a muscle is contracted or it's shortened to 75% up to breast length,
값이 0.75라면, 근육이 수축되어 정지 길이의 75%까지 짧아졌을 때를 의미합니다.
then we consider that as maximal contraction.
그 시점을 최대 수축으로 간주합니다.
So these are the things you can tweak when you're designing your simulation looks.
따라서 시뮬레이션의 모습을 설계할 때 이런 값들을 조정하면 됩니다.
And lastly, we also have inflation volume scale.
마지막으로 'Inflation Volume Scale'도 있습니다.
This controls the breast volume.
이는 팽창 볼륨(부풀어 오르는 정도)을 제어합니다.
So for the sake of the tutorial, let's just make that 3.
튜토리얼에서는 값을 3으로 설정하겠습니다.
Then you should see the effect immediately.
그러면 바로 효과를 확인할 수 있습니다.
You see the muscle is already gaining volume at breast state.
보시다시피 근육이 이미 기본 상태에서도 볼륨이 증가하는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
That's good.
좋습니다.
We can also control individual muscle behaviors.
개별 근육의 동작도 제어할 수 있습니다.
So what we showed here was a global tweak to all of the muscles.
여기까지는 모든 근육에 적용되는 글로벌 조정이었습니다.
So what if we only want to change behaviors on the bicep?
그럼 이두근에만 동작 변화를 주고 싶다면 어떻게 할까요?
So we can do that through the custom parameters here.
여기 'Custom Parameters'로 할 수 있습니다.
Here we can change muscle parameters for only the bicep by clicking this to import all muscle names.
이 버튼으로 모든 근육 이름을 가져온 다음, 이두근만 선택해서 해당 파라미터를 바꿀 수 있습니다.
So this will load all the muscles.
이렇게 하면 모든 근육이 불러와집니다.
So both bicep and pectoralis.
이두근, 대흉근 모두요.
Let's identify the bicep by clicking it.
이두근을 클릭해서 선택해 봅시다.
And then we should review the name of it called 58 at 57.
그리고 이름이 '58 at 57'로 되어 있는지 확인합니다.
If you look through here, that would be this one right here.
여기 목록에서 보면 바로 이 항목입니다.
So we can delete the first one.
그래서 첫 번째 항목은 삭제하겠습니다.
That's deleted.
삭제됐습니다.
And now it's only the bicep that's left.
이제 이두근만 남았습니다.
So over here we can change some muscle parameters for just that.
여기에서 이 근육에 대해서만 파라미터를 일부 변경할 수 있습니다.
Let's make sure we change the breast volume to 3.
여기 팽창 볼륨을 3으로 바꿔줍시다.
If we do that, let's make sure we apply custom parameters.
그렇게 했다면, 'Custom Parameters' 적용을 확인하세요.
Because now we're overriding the global parameters.
이제 글로벌 파라미터를 덮어쓰게 되거든요.
And if we click record, now you should see that's changed.
'Record'를 누르면 변경 사항이 반영된 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
So that's good.
좋네요.
This gives us a way to individually modify muscle behavior.
이처럼 각 근육의 동작을 개별적으로 수정할 수 있게 됩니다.